这里再次是我们简单的双连杆平面机器人，我们现在要做的是
Here again is our simple two-link planar robot and what we're going to do now is to
将末端执行器速度视为一组非常特定的关节速度的函数。
consider the end effector velocity as a function of a very specific set of joint velocities.
这是一组幅度为1的联合速度。我们可以考虑这个问题
That's the set of joint velocities that have got a magnitude of 1. We can think about this
几何。我们感兴趣的是所有速度的集合
geometrically. What we're interested in is the set of all velocities that lie on this
红色圆圈。以下是该圈子的一般要点Q.指向这里和这里
red circle. Here is a general point Q that lies on that circle. Points here and here
仅对应于关节1的运动，这里的点对应于运动
corresponds to motion of joint 1 only and points here and here corresponds to motion
仅关节2。圆圈中的所有其他点对应于运动的混合
of joint 2 only. All the other points in the circle correspond to a mixture of motion of
关节1和关节2。
joint 1 and of joint 2.
我们可以写出这个约束的另一种方法是速度位于红色圆圈上
Another way we could write this constraint that the velocity lies on the red circle is
就该载体而言，载体产物。它与点积相同。相同的点积
in terms of this vector, vector product. It's the same as the dot product. Same dot product
Qdot与其本身的等于1.我们有一个关于雅可比的Qdot的表达式
of Qdot with itself is equal to 1. We have an expression for Qdot in terms of the Jacobian
矩阵逆和机器人末端执行器的速度。所以我可以替换这个表达式
matrix inverse and the velocity of the robot end effector. So I can substitute this expression
对于上面的Qdot，我得到一个看起来像这样的复杂表达式。
for Qdot into the above and I get a complex expression that looks like this.
那是什么意思？那么这是椭圆的等式。它是速度的椭圆
What does that mean? Well this is the equation for an ellipse. It's an ellipse in the velocity
空间。所以在坐标系xdot和ydot中，我们这里有一个表达式
space. So in the coordinate system xdot and ydot, what we have here is an expression for
椭圆。所以这是椭圆xdot和ydot上的特定速度。发生了什么
an ellipse. So this is a particular velocity on that ellipse xdot and ydot. What happened
我们是否在关节空间中绘制了一组速度，这是一个圆圈
is we've mapped a set of velocities in the joint space which was a circle into a set
最终效应器速度空间中的速度和椭圆。这说的是什么
of velocities in the end effector velocity space and that is an ellipse. What this says
是机器人能够在y方向上达到相当高的速度但相对而言
is that the robot was able to achieve quite a high speed in the y direction but a relatively
x方向低速。因此它可以在y方向上快速前进，在x方向上更慢。
low speed in the x direction. So it can go fast in the y direction and more slowly in the x direction.
现在我绘制的这个椭圆是关节角度配置的函数。形状
Now this ellipse that I've drawn is a function of the joint angle configuration. The shape
椭圆的大小取决于机器人关节角度的配置方式。
of the ellipse depends on the way the robot joint angles are configured.
让我们来看看这个例子，以获得这背后的直觉。再次，这是我们的双链机器人。
Let's have a look at the example to get the intuition behind this. Once again, this is our two-linked robot.
如果我移动关节1，那么链接1的末端将以这样的速度移动。和
And if I moved joint 1 then the end of link 1 will move with the velocity like this. And
如果我移动关节2，那么链接2的末端将以这样的速度移动。结束
if I move joint 2 then the end of link 2 will move with the velocity like this. The end
效应器速度是这两个速度的矢量和。我们可以添加两个向量
effector velocity is the vector sum of these two velocities. We can add the two vectors
这是结果。
together and this is the resultant.
而我们在这种特殊配置中看到的机器人能够更快地移动
And what we see in this particular configuration, the robot was able to move more quickly in
垂直方向比水平方向。所以对于相等的关节速度，
the vertical direction than it can do in the horizontal direction. So for equal joint velocities,
我们通常会在不同的笛卡尔方向上获得均匀的速度。这取决于
we will in general get an even velocity in the different Cartesian directions. This depends
关于机器人的配置。
on the robot's configuration.
让我们看看机器人的速度椭圆如何随机器人的配置而变化
Let's have a look at how the robot's velocity ellipse changes shape as the robot's configuration
变化。我已经导入了双连杆平面机械手的模型。我策划并创作了
changes. I've imported a model of the two-linked planar manipulator. I plotted and I created
这里有一个教学窗口。所以我们可以看到侧面的蓝色面板有两个滑块
a teach window here. So we can see the blue panel on the side has got a couple of sliders
这让我可以改变机器人的关节角度。这是一个简单的看法。自上而下
that allow me to change the joint angles of the robot. This is a plain view. A top down
机器人机械手的视图。
view of the robot manipulator.
我要做的第一件事就是稍微调整关节1滑块。在这里我们可以看到
First thing I'm going to do is to adjust the joint 1 slide a little bit. Here we can see
机器人的速度椭圆。它确实非常非常瘦。那是因为机器人是
the robot's velocity ellipse. It's very, very skinny indeed. That's because the robot is
在一个接近奇异的条件下。我们看到在这样的配置中，机器人能够
at a near singular condition. We see that in configuration like this, the robot is able
向左和向右移动很快。但它几乎完全无法完成
to move quite quickly towards the left and the right. But it's almost completely unable
向上或向下移动。这里的配置接近于奇点和相似性
to move either upwards or downwards. The configuration here is close to singularity and similarity
当第二个关节角度非常接近0时出现。让我增加第二个
came about when the second joint angle was very close to 0. Let me increase the second
关节角度。现在将要发生的是椭圆越来越宽。
joint angle. What's going to happen now is that the ellipse gets wider and wider.
机器人远离奇点，现在处于关节角度的配置
The robot is further away from singularity and is now in a configuration of joint angles
这使得它可以很容易地沿着链路2的方向移动或者与链路正交
that allows it to move quite readily along the direction of link 2 or orthogonal to link
2.现在，如果我减小第二个关节角度Q2，使其接近0，我们看到椭圆
2. Now if I reduce the second joint angle, Q2, make it close to 0, we see that the ellipse
将变得更瘦，更瘦。最终它将成为一条直线为0的椭圆。
is going to get skinnier and skinnier. Ultimately it will become an ellipse of 0 with a straight line.